A Guide to the Correspondence of Ezra and Dorothy Pound, 1951-1954
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Correspondence of Ezra and Dorothy Pound, 1951-1954
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
8207-f
This collection consists of 19 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was purchased by the Library from Franklin Gilliam Rare Books on July 13, 1995.
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains fourteen letters, notes, and postal cards from Ezra Pound to Virginia Moore, one letter from Moore to Ezra Pound, and four letters from Dorothy Pound to Virginia Moore all written during the time that Pound was a patient in St. Elizabeth's in Washington D.C.
Pound discusses the magazine "Intro," William Butler Yeats, Pound's work on Confucius, World War II, and Italian travel. Dorothy Pound comments on Moore's book on Yeats and her youthful friendship with Georgie Hyde-Lees Yeats. In her letter to Pound, Moore disputes Pound's comments on books she lent him, his dismissal of modern philosophy, and his interpretation of Judaism and Christianity as solely legalistic.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Ezra Pound Letters
  - Ezra Pound, Washington, D.C. to Virginia Moore, Scottsville, Virginia 1951 Jul 30, 1 p., with envelope, TL
    Answers questions about William Butler Yeats, "less important to know his kinks than to spotlight the vital part, i.e. that still NEEDED (and how) to 'save the world'" and lists three key ideas in Yeats' work.
  - Ezra Pound, Washington, D.C. to Virginia Moore, Scottsville, Virginia 1951 Aug 16, 1 p., with envelope, TL
    Discusses the delay in the publication of Confucius: The Great Learning and the Unwobbling Pivot by New Directions; the absence of his name on his adaptations of the translations by Ernest Fenollosa of the Chinese poet Li Po; the banning of Kung Fu-tse (Confucius) in both the private and public schools of Red China; and complains about the United States "where they print a bibliography BEFORE they print major works? AND the universities WANT it that way."
  - Ezra Pound, Washington, D.C. to Virginia Moore, Stamford, Connecticut 1951 Dec 8, 1 p., APCS
    Pound writes "Had been wondering. E.P."
  - Ezra Pound, Washington, D.C. to Virginia Moore, Stamford Connecticut 1951 Dec 9, 2p., with envelope, TL
    Asks Moore to risk a subscription to Intro edited by Brigante, Shorter, and Elath and published in New York; mentions the Square Dollar Series, the proposal of a reprint of Guide to Kulchur with a few addenda by New Directions; and refers to the Stone Classics, "The STONE looks vurry handsome, lets hope it will FALL on wicked and grind a few of 'em to powder. The MORE important work still stalled in print shop/ and the endowments stink ever yet more stinkingly under the totally imperceptive nose of the denizens." The letter ends with a handwritten greeting.
  - Ezra Pound, Washington, D.C., to Virginia Moore, Stamford Connecticut 1951 Dec 14, 1 p., with envelope, TLS
    Estimates that six hundred dollars is needed to save Intro from extinction, which could be paid quarterly, "Happier to use MINIMUM $, and thereby oppose idea that $ can all. ONLY fr/sad/ experience better to have the $600 sure and not depend on patron's emotions after editor shows tendency to straye from the beaten or unbeaten etc/". The letter ends with an handwritten greeting.
  - Ezra Pound, Washington, D.C., to Virginia Moore, Stamford, Connecticut 1951 Dec 21, 1 p., with envelope, TN
    Pound discusses Intro, "Seems to be drawbacks re/ INTRO, buTTTT, go on looking for Maple trees/ may be something better can be found to run the sap into. The NEED remains, even if solution not immediate to hand."
  - Ezra Pound, Washington, D.C. to Virginia 1952 Jan 12, 1 p., with envelope, TN
    Expresses the need for a serious forum for ideas and states that if one were "solid' on several basic authors, listing Kung, Mencius, Dante, Blackstone, and Agassiz, "you wdn't be bothered by passing fads."
  - Ezra Pound, Washington, D.C., to Virginia Moore, Stamford, Connecticut 1952 Jan 17, 1 p., with envelope, ANS
    Pound writes, "Sorry no strength to write at all - hope to see you EP."
  - Ezra Pound, Washington, D.C. to Virginia Moore, Stamford, Connecticut 1952 Mar 3, 1 p., with envelope, ANS
    Pound offers advice about her proposed visit to Italy, mentioning Rome, Sicily, Palermo and Naples.
  - Ezra Pound, Washington, D.C., to Virginia Moore, Stamford, Connecticut, but forwarded to Scottsville, Virginia 1952 Jun 1, 1 p., with envelope, TN
    Asks if Moore knows of a music hall "capable of carrying on Rapallo music work, aim permanent local center?" or "anyone controlling a WALL? i.e. surface capable of enabling right kind of paint?"
  - Ezra Pound, Washington, D.C. to Virginia Moore, Scottsville, Virginia 1952 Jun 10, 1 p., with envelope, ALS
    Pound complains "Watts is an ass but the London Slimes outdoes itself in the squalor of its imbecility. & there are no polemical writers to correct this imbecility."
  - Ezra Pound, Washington, D.C. to Virginia Moore, Scottsville, Virginia 1952 Aug 24, 1 p., with envelope, TL
    Pound appears to be discussing the World War II period, "Yu canNOT get the whole view in 2 hours. Perhaps the worst crime of the ruling swine was the effort to keep (and success in keeping) infomation from the american people / AND even from those repsonsible for deciding govt. action. As to the accumulation of ignorance / take Memoirs of Hull (1), Stilwell (2), Leahy (3), Mme de Chambrun (4) a cross section of ruling class/ 1) honest hillbilly, better than the dam barflies that by-passed him 2) good guy, 3) rubber stamp, 4) mondaine ALL ham ignorant of data that should have been lammed into 'em in high school."
  - Ezra Pound, Washington, D. C., to Virginia Moore, Scottsville, Virginia 1952 Sep 4, 2 p. with envelope, TLS, and an enclosed card, ANS
    Pound discusses William Butler Yeats and the influence of Giovanni Gentile, Minister of Education under Mussolini, and Benedetto Croce upon his work, "question whether Yeats left any intelligent notes re / Gentile, esp/ that wd/ lead to thesis that Gentile stood for a return to philoSOPHY as distinct from centuries of totally sterile twaddle re philoEPISTEMOLOGY. I know that Y/ thought he was getting somewhere, after bobbling round and reading some Croce etc/ he found Gentile a step forward." Pound also mentions Bergson, Nietzsche, James, Dewey, Hegel, and Winston Churchill and concludes with "apart from a few facts he picked up in Oirish senate, WBY, so far as I know, eschewed everything I consider of primarily worth study, i.e. reading, as distinct from contemplation, during the last 15 years of his life." Also present on the back of the letter is a handwritten note from Dorothy Pound. There is also and enclosed card [Sep?] 19, "Thanks for [Japanese] No book Ez P-"
  - Ezra Pound, Washington, D.C. to Virginia Moore, Scottsville, Virginia 1953 Dec 1, 1 p. with envelope, ANS
    Pound thanks Virginia for a cake.
- Dorothy Pound Letters
  - Dorothy Pound, Washington, D.C. to Virginia Moore, Scottsville, Virginia 1952 Jun 7, 3 p., on 1 l., with envelope, ALS
    Recieved the card from Edith Johnson and urges Virginia to get well, hopes she enjoyed Europe, "the p. card of Segesta has been much used to educate in the matter of proportion" and notes that Ezra has just read some of William Butler Yeats' later work and liked the Casement poems.
  - Dorothy Pound, Washington, D.C. to Virginia Moore, Scottsville, Virginia 1952 Jul 4, 3 p. on 2 l., with envelope, ALS
    Writes that Moore's illness sounded like Malta fever; mentions the heat and her visits to St. Elizabeth's, "E P can't get out unless I am there to prevent his escaping. He doesn't mind the heat," William Butler Yeats' wife, Georgie Hyde-Lees Yeats, "Am interested that you met Georgie WBY. We spent many holiday times together in our young youths. But later got diverted - by our poet-husbands! (I don't mean quarrelled)."
  - Dorothy Pound, Washington, D.C., to Virginia Moore, Scottsville, Virginia 1953 May 22, 1 p., APCS
    She writes, "Thanks so much for the Kung pictures... interesting - Saw Eliz. W. who said she had sent you notice of M. Sommes death - I believe the Bk of changes was for divination. Mary's 2 months' visit was a great pleasure for EP. She seems a solid sort of character."
  - Dorothy Pound, Washington, D.C. to Virginia Moore, New York 1955 Jan 9, 1 p. with envelope, ALS
    She responds to Moore's book about William Butler Yeats The Unicorn"You don't distinguish between friendliness and friendship. I have so much more to get through daily, than I have strength for - that I omitted to accuser reception. I must have told you? that I am sick to death of W.B.Y. & shouldn't dream of reading about him. I also regret having let you print certain paragraphs.. .but since that is the kind of stuff (one might almost say, the only kind of stuff) that sells ---- I do certainly wish you a fine exciting journey -"
- Virginia Moore Letter
  - Virginia Moore, Scottsville, Virginia, to Ezra Pound 1954 Jan 25, 3 p. on 3 l., TL (Carbon)
    Moore writes concerning two books she had lent Pound who regarded them as of no interest, a Wadler book on linguistics and [William Howard?] Steiner's book on world economics; seeing Omar and Dorothy Pound at Christmas; and takes Pound to task over several sweeping statements about modern philosophy, such as "No good from any ism" (except Confucian ism!), and about religion "Christianity just follows the legalism of Judaism." Moore follows with a long response, "Well, I can understand why a person should react strongly against the Christian churches. But I can't understand how anyone who has studied throroughly the Old and New Testament (and until he has he hasn't a right to an opinion) can say thay Judaism is solely a legalism. Deuteronomy and tradition, yes. But the Old Testament has two strains, two elements,: the legalistic and 'prophetic,' the latter to be found at its best in parts of Isaiah. It's onto the prophetic part that Christianity- true Christianity, not Christendom- hooks."